I was told to come here and tell you all stories,
لقد قيل لي أن أحضر إلى هنا وأخبركم قصصًا،
but what I'd like to do is instead tell you why I'm suspicious of stories,
لكن ما أود أن أخبركم به بدلا من ذلك هو لِمَ تثير القصص الشك لدي.
why stories make me nervous.
لِمَ تجعلني القصص عصبيًا.
In fact, the more inspired a story makes me feel,
في الحقيقة، كلما جعلتني قصة ما أشعر بالإلهام،
very often, the more nervous I get.
كلما ازدادت عصبيتي في أكثر الأحيان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the best stories are often the trickiest ones.
غالبًا أفضل القصص هي الأكثر خداعا.
The good and bad things about stories is that they are a kind of filter.
الأمر السيء والجيد عن القصص أنها نوعًا ما كالمصفاة.
They take a lot of information, and they leave some of it out,
فهي تأخذ الكثير من المعلومات، وتهملُ بعضًا منها،
and they keep some of it in.
وتحتفظُ بالبعض.
But the thing about this filter is that it always leaves the same things in.
لكن الأمر حول هذه المصفاة هو أنها دومًا تحتفظُ بنفس الأشياء.
You're always left with the same few simple stories.
دائمًا ما تجد بعض القصص البسيطة نفسها.
There is the old saying that just about every story
هناك مقولة قديمة حول كل قصة تقريبًا
can be summed up as "a stranger came to town."
يمكن أن تُختصر في: "أتى غريبٌ إلى المدينة."
There is a book by Christopher Booker,
هناك كتاب لكريستوفر بوكر،
where he claims there are really just seven types of stories.
حيث يدّعي أنه يوجد في الواقع سبعة أنواع من القصص فقط.
There is monster, rags to riches, quest,
يوجد الوحش، والفقر إلى الثراء، والبحث،
voyage and return, comedy, tragedy, rebirth.
والرحلة والعودة، والهزل، المأساة، والولادة من جديد.
You don't have to agree with that list exactly,
ليس بالضرورة أن تتفق تمامًا مع هذه القائمة،
but the point is this: if you think in terms of stories,
لكن المغزى هو أنك إذا فكرت من حيث القصص،
you're telling yourself the same things over and over again.
فستظل تخبر نفسك نفس الأشياء مرارًا وتكرارًا.
There was a study done, we asked some people--
لقد تم عمل دراسة، حيث سألنا بعض الناس
people were asked to describe their lives.
طُلب من الناس أن يصفوا حياتهم.
When asked to describe their lives,
حين طُلب منهم أن يصفوا حياتهم،
what is interesting is how few people said "mess".
المثير في الأمر هو أن عدد قليل وصف حياته "فوضى".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's probably the best answer, I don't mean that in a bad way.
محتمل أن هذه هي أفضل إجابة، لا أقصد ذلك بمعنًى سيء.
"Mess" can be liberating, "mess" can be empowering,
يمكنُ للفوضى أن تكون محرّرة، ويمكن لها أن تكون تمكينًا،
"mess" can be a way of drawing upon multiple strengths.
يمكنُ للفوضى أن تكون وسيلة للاستفادة من نقاط قوى متعددة.
But what people wanted to say was, "My life is a journey."
لكن ما أراد الناس قوله كان، "حياتي رحلة".
51% wanted to turn his or her life into a story.
أراد 51% تحويل حياتهم إلى قصة.
11% said, "My life is a battle." Again, that is a kind of story.
وقال 11%: "حياتي كفاح" وهذا أيضا كالقصة نوعًا ما.
8% said, "My life is a novel." 5% said, "My life is a play."
وقال 8% : "حياتي رواية" وقال 5%: "حياتي مسرحية".
I don't think anyone said, "My life is a reality TV show."
لا أظن أن أحدًا قال: " حياتي برنامج تلفازي واقعي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But again, we're imposing order on the mess we observe,
لكن مجددًا، نحن نفرض النظام على الفوضى التي نلحظها،
and it's taking the same patterns,
وتأخدُ نفس الأنماط،
and the thing is when something is in the form of a story,
والفكرة هي عندما يكون الشيء في صيغة قصة،
often, we remember it when we shouldn't.
غالبا ما نتذكرها حين لا يجدر بنا ذلك.
So how many of you know the story
لذا كم منكم يعرف القصة
about George Washington and the cherry tree?
عن جورج واشنطن وشجرة الكرز؟
It's not obvious that is exactly what happened.
ليس واضحًا هذا ما حدث بالتحديد.
The story of Paul Revere, it's not obvious that that is exactly the way it happened.
قصة بول ريفير، ليس واضحًا طريقة حدوثها تمامًا.
So again, we should be suspicious of stories.
لذا مجددًا، علينا أن نتوخى حذرنا تجاه القصص.
We're biologically programmed to respond to them.
نحن مبرمجون بيولوجيًا لكي نستجيب لها.
They contain a lot of information. They have social power.
إنها تحتوي على العديد من المعلومات، ولديها قوة اجتماعية.
They connect us to other people.
إنها تربطنا بأناس آخرين.
So they are like a candy that we're fed
فإنها كالحلوى التي نتناولها
when we consume political information, when we read novels.
عندما تشغل بالنا المعلومات السياسية، وعندما نقرأ الروايات.
When we read non-fiction books, we're really being fed stories.
عندما نقرأ القصص الواقعية، اكتفينا حقًا من القصص.
Non-fiction is, in a sense, the new fiction.
القصص الواقعية في جوهرها هي خيال جديد.
The book may happen to say true things,
ربما يقول الكتاب شيئا صادقًا،
but again, everything's taking the same form of these stories.
لكن مجددًا، يأخذ كل شيء نفس شكل هذه القصص.
So what are the problems of relying too heavily on stories?
فما هي المشاكل في اعتمادنا على القصص بشكلٍ كبير.
You view your life like this
أنت ترى حياتك بهذا الشكل
instead of the mess that it is or it ought to be.
بدلًا من الفوضى كما هي، أو كما من المفترض أن تكون.
But more specifically, I think of a few major problems
لكن بالتحديد أكثر، أفكر في بعض المشاكل الكبرى
when we think too much in terms of narrative.
عندما نفكر أكثر من اللازم من حيث سرد القصص.
First, narratives tend to be too simple,
أولا، يميل سرد القصص أن يكون بسيطًا للغاية،
for the point of a narrative is to strip it away,
لأن هدف القصة هو تجريد المغزى،
not just into 18 minutes,
ليس فقط في 18 دقيقة،
but most narratives you can present in a sentence or two.
ولكن يمكنُ تعريف معظم القصص في جملة أو اثنتين.
When you strip away detail,
عندما تجرد القصة من التفاصيل،
you tend to tell stories in terms of good versus evil,
فإنك غالبًا ما تروي القصة من منظور الخير مقابل الشر،
whether it's a story about your own life or a story about politics.
سواءً كانت القصة عن حياتك الخاصة أو عن الأوضاع السياسية.
I know some things actually are good versus evil, we all know this, right?
أعلم أن بعض الأشياء هي فعلًا خير مقابل شر، يعلمُ كلنا هذا، أليس كذلك؟
But I think, as a general rule,
لكن في ظني كقاعدة عامة،
we're too inclined to tell the good versus evil story.
نحن مائلون لقول قصة تتحدثُ عن الخير مقابل الشر.
As a simple rule of thumb,
بحكم التجربة البسيطة،
just imagine that every time you're telling a good versus evil story,
فقط تخيل في كل مرة تروي قصة خير مقابل شر،
you're basically lowering your IQ by ten points or more.
فإنك بالأساس تقلل من معدل ذكائك بعشر نقاط أو أكثر.
If you just adopt that as a kind of inner mental habit,
وإذا تبنيت ذلك كنوع من العادة الذهنية،
it's, in my view, one way to get a lot smarter pretty quickly.
فإنها من وجهة نظري، أحد الطرق لتصبح أكثر ذكاءً بسرعة.
You don't have to read any books.
ليس عليك أن تقرأ أيّ كتب.
Just imagine yourself pressing a button
فقط تخيل نفسك تضغط على زر
every time you tell the good versus evil story,
في كل مرة تروي قصةً تتحدثُ عن الخير مقابل الشر،
and by pressing that button,
وبالضغط على ذلك الزر،
you're lowering your IQ by ten points or more.
فإنك تُقلّل معدل ذكائك بنسبة عشر نقاط أو أكثر.
Another set of stories that are popular--
هناك مجموعة أخرى من القصص الشعبية ..
if you know Oliver Stone's movies, or Michael Moore's movies,
إذا كنت تعرفُ أفلام أوليفر ستون، او أفلام مايكل مور،
you can't make a movie and say: "It was all a big accident."
لا يمكنك أن تصنع فيلما ثم تقول: "لقد كان الأمر كله مصادفة كبيرة."
No, it has to be a conspiracy, people plotting together,
لا، يجب أن تكون هناك مؤامرة، وأناسٌ يتآمرون معًا،
because in a story, a story is about intention.
لأنه في القصة، تكون القصة حول مخططٍ ما.
A story is not about spontaneous order or complex human institutions
ليست القصة عن النظام العفوي أو المؤسسات الإنسانية المعقدة
which are the product of human action, but not of human design.
التي هي نتاج الفعل البشري، ولكن ليس من صنع الإنسان.
No, a story is about evil people plotting together.
لا، تدور القصة عن الأشرار الذين يتآمرون معا.
So when you hear stories about plots,
لذا عندما تسمعُ قصصًا عن المكائد،
or even stories about good people plotting things together,
أو حتى عن أناس طيبين يخططون معًا،
just like when you're watching movies,
كما لو أنك تشاهد أفلامًا،
this, again, is reason to be suspicious.
ويكون هذا سببًا لتتوخى الحذر مجددًا.
As a good rule of thumb, if you're asking:
كقاعدة بسيطة، إذا كنتَ تسأل،
"When I hear a story, when should I be especially suspicious?"
"عندما أسمع قصةً ما، متى ينبغي أن أتوخى الحذر بشكلٍ خاص؟"
If you hear a story and you think: "Wow, that would make a great movie!"
إذا سمعت قصة وفكرت بأنه: "واو! من شأن ذلك أن يصنع فيلمًا رائعًا!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's when the "uh-oh" reaction should pop in a bit more,
حينها يجب أن تظهر تعابير المفاجأة والشك،
and you should start thinking in terms
وعليك أن تبدأ بالتفكير من منظور
of how the whole thing is maybe a bit of a mess.
كيف أن كل الأمر قد يكون عبارة عن جزء من الفوضى.
Another common story or storyline is the claim that we "have to get tough".
هناك قصة معروفة أخرى أو حبكة التي تدّعي: "علينا أن نصبح أكثر صرامة".
You'll hear this in so many contexts.
ستمسعُ ذلك في سياقات عديدة.
We have to get tough with the banks. We had to get tough with the labor unions.
يجبُ أن نكون أكثر صرامةً مع البنوك، وكان علينا التصرف بحزم مع اتحادات العمال.
We need to get tough with some other country,
ونحتاجُ لنكون أكثر صرامةً مع بعض الدول الأخرى.
some foreign dictator, someone we're negotiating with.
مع دكتاتورٍ غريب، ومع شخصٍ نتفاوض معه.
Again, the point is not against getting tough.
لا يتعارض المغزى مع أن نصبح أقوى أو أكثر صرامة.
Sometimes we should get tough.
علينا أحيانًا أن نصبح أكثر صرامة.
That we got tough with the Nazis was a good thing.
كان شيئا جيدًا أننا كنا أكثر صلابة مع النازيين.
But this is again a story we fall back upon all too readily, all too quickly.
لكن مجددًا، هذه قصة قد تراجعنا عنها جميعًا بسهولة وبسرعة.
When we don't really know why something happened,
عندما لا نعرف بالضبط سبب حدوث شيء ما،
we blame someone, and we say: "We need to get tough with them!"
فإننا تلقي اللوم على شخصٍ ما، ونقول: "نحتاجُ لأن نصبح أكثر صرامة معهم!"
As if it had never occurred to your predecessor,
وكأن نفس الشيء لم يحدث أبدًا لمن سبقوك،
this idea of getting tough.
هذه الفكرة بأن نصبح أكثر صرامة.
I view it usually as a kind of mental laziness.
أراها عادةً كنوع من الكسل الذهني.
It's a simple story you tell: "We need to get tough,
إنها قصة بسيطة أن تقول: "نحتاج أن نكون أكثر صرامة،
we needed to get tough, we will have to get tough."
كان علينا أن نكون أكثر صرامة، ويجب أن نصبح أكثر صرامة"
Usually, that is a kind of warning signal.
عادةً، يشبه ذلك جرس الإنذار.
Another kind of problem with stories is
مشكلة أخرى مع القصص هي
you can only fit so many stories into your mind at once,
يمكنك حفظ الكثير من القصص في عقلك مرة واحدة،
or in the course of a day, or even over the course of a lifetime.
أو على مدار اليوم، أو حتى طيلة حياتك.
So your stories are serving too many purposes.
وبهذا تخدمُ قصصك الكثير من الأغراض.
For instance, just to get out of bed in the morning,
على سبيل المثال، فقط لكي تنهض من على السرير في الصباح،
you tell yourself the story
فأنت تروي لنفسك قصة
that your job is really important, what you're doing is really important
أن وظيفتك مهمَّة حقاً، وأن ما تفعله ضروريٌ جدًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and maybe it is, but I tell myself that story even when it's not.
وقد يكون كذلك بالفعل، لكنّي أخبر نفسي تلك الحكاية حتى عندما لا يكون كذلك.
And you know what? That story works.
أتعلمون؟ تلك الطريقة فعالة.
It gets me out of bed.
إنها السبب في نهوضي من السرير.
It's a kind of self-deception,
إنها نوع من خداع الذات،
but the problem comes when I need to change that story.
لكن المشكلة تظهر حين أحتاج إلى تغيير القصة.
The whole point of the story is that I grab onto it and I hold it,
إن المغزى الوحيد من القصة هو أن أتشبث بها،
and it gets me out of bed.
فتجعلني أنهض من السرير.
So when I'm really doing something that is actually just a waste of time,
لذا فعندما أفعل شيئا هو حقاً مضيعة للوقت،
in my mess of a life,
في فوضى حياتي،
I'm too tied into my story that got me out of bed,
أكون قد تعلّقت بشكلٍ زائد بتلك القصة التي جعلتني أنهض من السرير،
and ideally, I ought to have some very complex story map in my mind,
ومن ناحية المثالية، يجب أن تكون لدي خريطة قصة معقدة في ذهني،
you know, with combinatorials and a matrix of computation, and the like,
كما تعلمون، كما في التوافقيات ومصفوفة الحساب وما يشبهها،
but that is not how stories work.
لكن ليس هكذا تجري القصص.
Stories in order to work have to be simple,
كي تؤدي القصص الغرض منها يجب أن تكون بسيطة،
easily grasped, easily told to others, easily remembered.
سهلة الإدراك، يسهل روايتها للآخرين، ويسهل تذكّرها.
So stories will serve dual and conflicting purposes,
لذا فإن القصص قد تخدم غرضين متناقضين،
and very often they will lead us astray.
وفي أحيانٍ كثيرة، سوف تقوم بتضليلنا.
I used to think I was within the camp of economists,
لقد كنت أعتقد أنني ضمن مجموعة الاقتصاديين،
I was one of the good guys, and I was allied with other good guys,
كنت أحد أولئك الشباب الجيدين، وكنت متحالفا مع شباب جيدين آخرين،
and we were fighting the ideas of the bad guys.
وكنا نحارب أفكار "الشباب الأشرار".
I used to think that!
اعتدت أن أفكر بهذه الطريقة!
And probably, I was wrong.
ومن المحتمل أني كنت مخطئا.
Maybe sometimes, I'm one of the good guys,
ربما أحيانا، أكون أحد أولئك الشباب الأخيار،
but on some issues, I finally realized: "Hey, I wasn't one of the good guys."
لكن في بعض المسائل، أدركت أخيرا: "مهلًا، أنا لم أكن واحدا من الأخيار."
I'm not sure I was the bad guy in the sense of having evil intent,
لست متأكداً إن كنت الشخص السيء بمعنى أن لدي نيّة شريرة،
but it was very hard for me to get away with that story.
لكنّه كان صعبًا علي أن أنصرف عن هذه القصة.
One interesting thing about cognitive biases
الشيء المثير عن الانحياز الإدراكي
is they are the subject of so many books these days.
هو أنه موضوع العديد من الكتب هذه الأيام.
There's the Nudge book, the Sway book, the Blink book,
هناك كتاب الوكز، وكتاب الهيمنة، وكتاب الطرفة،
like the one-title book,
مثل كتاب العنوان الوحيد،
all about the ways in which we screw up.
جميعها عن الطرق التي تحدث بها اخفاقاتنا.
And there are so many ways,
وهناك العديد من الطرق،
but what I find interesting is that none of these books identify
ولكن ما وجدته مثيرًا للاهتمام هو أنه لم تحدّد أي من هذه الكتب
what, to me, is the single, central, most important way we screw up,
ما هي الطريقة المركزية الوحيدة الأهم بالنسبة لي التي تسبب اخفاقنا،
and that is that we tell ourselves too many stories,
وهي أننا نروي لأنفسنا قصصا عدة،
or we are too easily seduced by stories.
أو أننا نقع فريسة إغراء القصص بسهولة شديدة.
Why don't these books tell us that?
لماذا لا تخبرنا هذه الكتب ذلك؟
It's because the books themselves are all about stories.
ذلك بسبب أن الكتب نفسها تدور حول القصص.
The more of these books you read, you're learning about some of your biases,
كلما قرأت هذه النوعية أكثر، فأنت تعرف عن بعض تحيزاتك،
but you're making some of your other biases essentially worse.
ولكنك أساسًا تعملُ على جعل بعض تحيزاتك الأخرى أكثر سوءًا
So the books themselves are part of your cognitive bias.
لذلك فالكتب نفسها هي بعض من تحيزاتك الإدراكية.
Often, people buy them as a kind of talisman, like:
غالبا، يشتريها الناس كنوع من الطلاسم، مثل:
"I bought this book. I won't be 'Predictably Irrational'."
"اشتريت هذا الكتاب. سوف لن أكون لا عقلانيا على نحو متوقع."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's like people want to hear the worst,
كما لو أن الناس يريدون سماع الأسوأ،
so psychologically, they can prepare for it or defend against it.
حتى يستطيعوا الاستعداد له أو حماية أنفسهم منه من ناحية نفسية،
It's why there is such a market for pessimism.
هذا هو السبب في وجود هذا النوع من التشاؤم.
But to think that by buying the book gets you somewhere,
لكن أن تظن أنه شرائك الكتاب سيوصلك إلى مكانٍ ما،
that's maybe the bigger fallacy.
فلربما كانت تلك هي المغالطة الكبرى.
It's just like the evidence that shows that the most dangerous people
يبدو الأمرُ تمامًا مثل الدليل الذي يظهرُ أن الأشخاص الأكثر خطورة
are those who have been taught some financial literacy.
هم أولئك الذين تم تلقينهم بعض المعرفة المالية.
They're the ones who go out and make the worst mistakes.
هم أولئك الذين يقترفون أسوأ الأخطاء.
It's the people who realize they don't know anything at all,
هم الأشخاص الذين يدركون أنهم لا يعرفون شيئا على الإطلاق،
that end up doing pretty well.
والذين ينتهي بهم المطاف بفعل أشياء بشكلٍ جيد.
A third problem with stories
المشكلة الثالثة حول القصص
is that outsiders manipulate us using stories,
هي أن الدخلاء يتلاعبون بنا باستخدام القصص،
and we all like to think advertising only works on the other guy,
وجميعنا يحب أن يعتقد أن الدعاية تنجح فقط مع الشخص الآخر،
but, of course, that's not how it is, advertising works on all of us.
ولكن بالتأكيد، ليس الأمر كذلك، لأن الدعاية تنجح مع الجميع.
So if you're too attached to stories,
لذا إذا كنت متعلقًا جدًا بالقصص،
what will happen is people selling products come along,
ما سيحدث هو أن بيع الناس للمنتجات سيظهر جنبًا إلى جنب القصص،
and they will bundle their product with a story.
وسيربطُ الناس منتجاتهم مع القصة.
You're like, "Hey, a free story!"
سيكون لسان حالك: "مهلًا، إنها قصة مجانية!"
And you end up buying the product,
وسينتهي بك الأمر بشراء المنتج،
because the product and the story go together.
لأن المنتج والقصة حزمة واحدة.
(Laugther)
(ضحك)
If you think about how capitalism works,
إذا ما كنتم تفكرون كيف تعمل الرأسمالية،
there is a bias here.
يوجد تحيز هنا.
Let's consider two kinds of stories about cars.
لنلقي النظر على نوعين من القصص عن السيارات.
Story A is: "Buy this car,
القصة أ هي: "اشترِ هذه السيارة،
and you will have beautiful, romantic partners and a fascinating life."
وسوف تحصل على شركاء جميلين ورومانسيين وحياة رائعة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There are a lot of people
هناك الكثير من الناس
who have a financial incentive to promote that story.
من يملكون حافزًا ماليا للترويج لتلك القصة.
But, say, the alternative story is:
لكن، لنقل، القصة البديلة هي:
"You don't actually need a car as nice as your income would indicate.
"في الواقع، لا تحتاج لسيارة جميلة كما يشيرُ إليه دخلك.
What you usually do is look at what your peers do and copy them.
ما يجب عليك فعله هو النظر إلى ما يفعله أقرانك وتقليدهم.
That is a good heuristic for lots of problems,
ذلك حدس مهني جيد للكثير من المشاكل،
but when it comes to cars, just buy a Toyota."
حينما يتعلق الأمر بالسيارات، اشتري تويوتا فقط."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe Toyota has an incentive there,
ربما كان لدى تويوتا حافزًا هناك،
but even Toyota is making more money off the luxury cars,
ولكن حتى التويوتا تحقق أرباحًا أكثر من السيارات الفاخرة،
and less money off the cheaper cars.
وأقل من السيارات الرخيصة.
So if you think which set of stories you end up hearing,
لذا إذا كنت تفكر أي نوع من القصص ستسمع إليها في آخر الأمر،
you end up hearing the glamor stories, the seductive stories,
سينتهي بك الأمر تسمع قصص السحر، والقصص المثيرة،
and again I'm telling you, don't trust them.
أخبرك مجددا، لا تثق بها.
There are people using your love of stories to manipulate you.
هناك أناس يستغلون حبك للقصص كي يتلاعبون بك.
Pull back and say:
تريث وقل:
"What are the messages,
ما هو المغزى،
what are the stories that no one has an incentive to tell?"
ما هي القصص التي لا يملك أي أحد دافعًا لحكيها؟"
Start telling yourself those, and then see if any of your decisions change.
ابدأ بإخبار نفسك هذه الأشياء، ثم لاحظ إن تغيرت أي من قراراتك.
That is one simple way.
تلك طريقة بسيطة.
You can never get out of the pattern of thinking in terms of stories,
لا يمكنك الهرب من نمط التفكير بخصوص القصص،
but you can improve the extent to which you think in stories,
ولكن يمكنك تحسين مدى اعتقادك في القصص،
and make some better decisions.
واتخاذ قرارات أفضل.
So if I'm thinking about this talk, I'm wondering, of course,
لذا إذا كنت أفكر في هذا الحديث، فأنا أتساءل بالتأكيد،
what is it you take away from this talk?
ماذا تستفيد من هذا الحديث؟
What story do you take away from Tyler Cowen?
ما هي القصة التي تخرج بها من تايلر كوين؟
One story you might be like the story of the quest.
قد تعجبك قصة واحدة هي قصة البحث.
"Tyler was a man on a quest.
"كان تايلر في مهمة بحث.
Tyler came here, and he told us not to think so much in terms of stories."
أتى تايلر إلى هنا وأخبرنا أن لا نفكر كثيرًا بخصوص القصص."
That would be a story you could tell about this talk.
ستكون تلك قصة يمكنك أن تحكيها عن هذا الحديث.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It would fit a pretty well-known pattern.
سيناسب ذلك نمطا رائعًا ذائع الصيت.
You might remember it. You could tell it to other people.
قد تتذكر ذلك، وقد تحكي ذلك لأشخاص آخرين.
"This weird guy came, and he said,
"أتى هذا الفتى الغريب وقال:
'Don't think in terms of stories. Let me tell you what happened today!'"
"لا تفكروا بخصوص القصص. دعوني أخبركم ما حدث اليوم!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you tell your story.
ثم تخبرهم بقصتك.
Another possibility is you might tell a story of rebirth.
الإمكانية الأخرى أن تحكي قصة عن الولادة من جديد.
You might say, "I used to think too much in terms of stories
قد تقول: "اعتدت أن أفكر كثيرًا بخصوص القصص
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but then I heard Tyler Cowen
كان ذلك قبل أن أستمع إلى تايلر كوين
and now I think less in terms of stories!"
ولكن الآن أفكر أقل بخصوص القصص!"
That too is a narrative you will remember,
تلك أيضا قصة ستتذكرها،
you can tell to other people, and again, it may stick.
قد تحكيها لأشخاص آخرين وقد تنتشر.
You also could tell a story of deep tragedy.
ربما تحكي أيضا قصة مأساة فظيعة.
"This guy Tyler Cowen came
"أتى هذا الفتى المدعو تايلر كوين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and he told us not to think in terms of stories,
وأخبرنا أن لا نفكر بخصوص القصص،
but all he could do was tell us stories
ولكن جلّ ما فعله هو أن حكى لنا قصصًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
about how other people think too much in terms of stories."
عن كيف أن الآخرين يفكرون دومًا بخصوص القصص."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, today, which is it? Is it like quest, rebirth, tragedy?
فاليوم، أيهم؟ هل يبدو مثل البحث، أو الولادة من جديد، أو المأساة؟
Or maybe some combination of the three?
أو ربما مزيج من الثلاثة معا؟
I'm really not sure, and I'm not here to tell you
لست متأكدًا حقًا ولست هنا لأطلب منكم
to burn your DVD player and throw out your Tolstoy.
أن تحرقوا مشغّل أقراص الفيديو الرقمية الخاص بكم أو أن ترموا كتب تولستوي.
To think in terms of stories is fundamentally human.
أن تفكّروا إنطلاقا من القصص هو شيء إنساني أساسي.
There is a Gabriel Garcia Marquez memoir "Living to Tell the Tale"
هناك السيرة الذاتية للكاتب غابرييل غارسيا ماركيز "عشتُ لأروي"
that we use memory in stories to make sense of what we've done,
حيث نستخدم الذكريات ضمن القصص لنجعل ما فعلناه منطقيًا،
to give meaning to our lives, to establish connections with other people.
لنعطي حياتنا معنى ولنخلق التواصل مع الآخرين.
None of this will go away, should go away, or can go away.
لن يضيع أي من هذا، ولا ينبغي أن يضيع، أو لا يمكنه الضياع.
But again, as an economist, I'm thinking about life on the margin,
ولكن مجددا كاقتصادي، أفكر في الحياة على أساس قيود الاسترخاء او التشدد/الهامش،
the extra decision.
قيمة القرار الإضافي.
Should we think more in terms of stories, or less in terms of stories?
هل يجب علينا أن نفكر أكثر بخصوص القصص، أو أقل بخصوص القصص؟
When we hear stories, should we be more suspicious?
عندما نسمع قصصًا، هل يجب أن نتوخى الحذر؟
And what kind of stories should we be suspicious of?
وما هو نوع القصص التي نجب أن نتوخى الحذر منها؟
Again, I'm telling you it's the stories, very often, that you like the most,
أخبركم مجددا أنها القصص التي تحبونها أكثر،
that you find the most rewarding, the most inspiring.
والتي تجدونها تستحق القراءة أكثر أو الأكثر إلهاما.
The stories that don't focus on opportunity cost,
القصص التي لا تركز على فرصة التكلفة،
or the complex, unintended consequences of human action,
أو التبعات المعقدة وغير المقصودة لتصرفات البشر،
because that very often does not make for a good story.
لأن ذلك غالبًا لا يصنع قصة جيدة.
So often a story is a story of triumph, a story of struggle;
عادة ما تكون القصة قصة انتصار أو نضال؛
there are opposing forces, which are either evil or ignorant;
هناك قوى مضادة، والتي هي إما شريرة أو جاهلة؛
there is a person on a quest, someone making a voyage,
هناك شخص في رحلة استكشافية، وشخص يقوم برحلة،
and a stranger coming to town.
ويأتي شخص غريب إلى المدينة.
And those are your categories, but don't let them make you too happy.
وتلك هي فئاتك، لكن لا تسمح لهم ليجعلوك سعيدًا للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As an alternative,
وكبديل،
at the margin - again, no burning of Tolstoy -
على الهامش - ومجددا، وبعيدا عن حرق كتب تولستوي -
but just be a little more messy.
كن فوضويا بعض الشيء.
If I actually had to live those journeys, and quests, and battles,
في الواقع، إن كان علي أن أخوض هذه الرحلات والمهام والمعارك
that would be so oppressive to me!
سيكون ذلك ظلمًا كبيرًا بالنسبة لي!
It's like, my goodness, can't I just have my life
يا إلهي، يشبه الأمر وكأنني لا أستطيع أن أعيش حياتي
in its messy, ordinary - I hesitate to use the word - glory
بحالتها الفوضوية، والإعتيادية - ترددت في استخدام الكلمة - ومجدها السابق
but that it's fun for me?
ولكن هل ذلك ممتع بالنسبة لي؟
Do I really have to follow some kind of narrative?
هل يجب علي حقًا أن أتبع قصة من نوع معين؟
Can't I just live?
ألا يمكنني أن أحيا فقط؟
So be more comfortable with messy.
فأشعر براحة أكثر مع الفوضى.
Be more comfortable with agnostic,
أشعر براحة أكثر مع الشك،
and I mean this about the things that make you feel good.
وهذا ما أعني بخصوص الأشياء التي تجعلك تشعرُ بشكلٍ أفضل.
It's so easy to pick out a few areas to be agnostic in,
من السهل جدا انتقاء بعض المجالات لتكون غير متأكد منها،
and then feel good about it,
ثم تشعر بالرضا حيالها،
like, "I am agnostic about religion, or politics."
مثل، "أنا غير متأكد فيما يتعلقُ بالدين أو السياسة".
It's a kind of portfolio move you make to be more dogmatic elsewhere, right?
إنها نوع من الحقيبة المتنقلة التي تجعلك أكثر تشدّدًا/دوغماتية في مكان آخر، أصحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sometimes,
أحيانا،
the most intellectually trustworthy people are the ones who pick one area,
الأشخاص الأكثر موثوقية من ناحية فكرية هم الذين يختارون مجالًا واحدًا،
and they are totally dogmatic in that, so pig-headedly unreasonable,
وهم مؤمنون متشددون حياله، وغنيدون على نحو مفرط،
that you think, "How can they possibly believe that?"
لدرجة تجعلك تفكر، "كيف يعقل أن يؤمنوا بذلك؟"
But it soaks up their stubbornness,
ولكن ذلك يرهقُ عنادهم،
and then, on other things, they can be pretty open-minded.
وفي أشياء أخرى يكونون أكثر انفتاحا.
So don't fall into the trap of thinking because you're agnostic on some things,
لذا لا تسقط في فخ التفكير بسبب أنك على غير يقين حيال بعض الأشياء،
that you're being fundamentally reasonable
كونك منطقي أساسًا
about your self-deception, your stories, and your open-mindedness.
حول الخداع الذاتي وقصصك وتفتح ذهنك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
[Think about] this idea of hovering, of epistemological hovering,
فكَر حول قضية التحليق هذه، المتعلقة بالتحليق المعرفي،
and messiness, and incompleteness,
والفوضوية وعدم الكمال،
[and how] not everything ties up into a neat bow,
وكيف أنه ليس كل الأشياء تنتهي نهاية سعيدة،
and you're really not on a journey here.
كما أنك لست في رحلة هنا.
You're here for some messy reason or reasons,
أنت هنا نتيجة سبب فوضوي أو أسباب،
and maybe you don't know what it is, and maybe I don't know what it is,
وربما لا تعرف ما هو، ولربما لا أعرف ما هو،
but anyway, I'm happy to be invited, and thank you all for listening.
ولكن على أي حال، أنا سعيد لدعوتي وأشكركم جميعا على حسن الاستماع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)